Harold Jones Collection of Salvador Dali and Joseph Forêt
Harold Jones Collection of Salvador Dali and Joseph Forêt
1956-1963
Jones, Harold Grover, 1941-
8 linear ft. (oversize flat boxes)
Artwork and memorabilia relating to surrealist artist Salvador Dali and his collaborations with French publisher Joseph Forêt on illustrated editions of La Divina Commedia (Dante), Don Quichotte de la Mancha (Cervantes), and L'Apocalypse de St. Jean. The material was collected by Syracuse University Professor Emeritus Harold Jones.
4878520
Biographical History
Harold Grover Jones (1941- ) is Professor Emeritus of Spanish at Syracuse University. He earned his PhD in Spanish Literature at Princeton in 1968. Prior to coming to Syracuse he taught at Macalester College, the University of Missouri, and the University of Houston, where he was chair of the Department of Hispanic and Classical Languages. He came to Syracuse University in 1988, where he served as chair of the department for nine years (1988 to 1997) and program coordinator of Spanish for the following six years.
Salvador Dali (1904-1989) was a prominent Spanish surrealist artist known for his striking and bizarre images. An eccentric and grandiose creative genius, he worked in a variety of media including printmaking and painting but also film, sculpture, and photography, and frequently collaborated with other artists.
Joseph Forêt was a French publisher. Between 1956 and 1963, he and Salvador Dalí collaborated to produce fine illustrated editions of Dante’s Divine Comedy, Cervantes’s Don Quixote, and Saint John’s Apocalypse. All three are notable for their size, lush artwork, attention to detail, and fine craftsmanship.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Harold Jones Collection of Salvador Dali and Joseph Forêt consists of artwork and a few items of memorabilia.
Artwork contains portfolios of prints from the La Divina Commedia, L'Apocalypse de St. Jean, and Don Quichotte (Don Quixote) and a few individual prints. There are also a few items by French artist Pierre-Yves Trémois.
Memorabilia contains photographs of Dali with Parisian publisher Joseph Forêt and a few items with Dali's signature.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged as necessary for appropriate storage and protection, but is listed in the inventory below in alphabetical order by type or title. Folders are numbered consecutively across the entire collection.
Separated Material
A number of published items have been transferred to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to and search on "Gift of Harold G. Jones" to locate these items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Painters; Publishing, printing and book arts; Cervantes Saavedra, Miguel de, 1547-1616.; Dalí, Salvador, 1904-1989.; Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321.; Foret, Joseph.; Jones, Harold Grover, 1941-; Trémois, Pierre Yves, 1921-; Bible. -- Revelation.; Art, Modern -- 20th century.; Illustration of books.; Painting, Modern -- 20th century.; Surrealism.; Grotesque in art.; Lithographs.; Memorabilia.; Printing plates.; Prints (visual works); Artists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of/purchase from Harold Jones, 2016.
Inventory
- Artwork
  - Portfolios
    - Blue portfolio, small, containing prints from copy A of Don Quichotte, 1957; 5 items (Oversize 4, Folder 1)
      Don Quixote L'Age Dor, on parchment
      Don Quixote L'Age Dor, on paper
      Attack on the windmills, on vellum[?]
      Unidentified, on paper (2 copies, appear to be identical)
    - Blue portfolio, large, containing prints from copy A of Don Quichotte de la Manche, 1957 (Oversize 4, Folder 2)
  - Prints
    - L'Apocalypse de St. Jean, "L'Hostie" [The Host] (Oversize 1, Folder 3)
    - L'Apocalypse de St. Jean, "La Pieta" (Oversize 3, Folder 4)
    - Don Quichotte de la Manche, 1957; a suite on Papier Japon Imperial of the 12 lithographs and the rare 13th lithograph "Exploding head of Don Quichotte"; 13 items (Oversize 1, Folder 5)
    - Inferno 18, "The Flatterer" (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
    - Paradiso 71, "Beatrice" (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
    - Purgatorio 29, "Meeting of Dante and Beatrice" (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
    - "Santiago el Grande," number 135 of 172, 1958 (Oversize 3, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified print on silk (Oversize 2)
  - Miscellaneous
    - L'Apocalypse, unidentified sketch, winged figure looking down and to the left, one hand on chest and one outstretched; includes pencil, pen, other media; annotated on back in French beginning "Le troisième [illegible] / Dieu [illegible] à l'agneau les destinées du monde..." (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
    - The End of Man / La Fin de l'homme, by Pierre-Yves Trémois, 1961 (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
    - The Locusts of Destruction / La Sauterelle apollyon, by Pierre-Yves Trémois, 1961; 2 versions, one gray and yellow and the other monochrome grays; 2 items (Oversize 1, Folder 6)
- Memorabilia
  - Money, signed by Dali, 2 items (Oversize 2)
  - Photographs (Oversize 2)
    Joseph Forêt holding copy of L'Apocalypse
    Joseph Forêt and Salvador Dali in Monaco
    Salvador Dali in Monaco
    Salvador Dali
  - Portrait of Dali, painted by street artist in India (Oversize 3, Folder 8)
  - Printing plate for Inferno 18, "The Flatterer", copper plate for this print, including Dali's signature at bottom center (Oversize 5, Folder 9)